Finding Aid for Felix J. Rogers Papers, 1982-2005
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Felix J. Rogers papers 1982-2005, 1987-2001
Rogers, Felix J., 1947-
1 oversize folders
7 linear feet
921069 Aa 2
Physician involved with peace organizations, notably Physicians for Social Responsibility, an organization opposed to nuclear weapons testing and the construction of nuclear power plants. Files relating to activities with the Physicians for Social Responsibility - Detroit, and with the Episcopal Peace Fellowship.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Dr. Felix J. Rogers (donor no. 7971 ) and came to the library in 1991 and 2009.
The collection is open to research.
Felix J. Rogers is a cardiologist who operates a private practice in Trenton, Michigan and a clinical professor of internal medicine at Michigan State University College of Osteopathic Medicine. In the 1980s, Rogers became involved with several peace organizations. He was an active member of Physicians for Social Responsibility (PSR) from 1982 until approximately 1996. He joined the executive committee of PSR-Detroit in 1985 and was elected chairman of the chapter in 1987. PSR was founded in Boston in 1961 by a group of Massachusetts physicians. Over the years, new regional chapters of this organization have been established including the Detroit chapter in the early 1980s. Nationally, PSR has opposed nuclear weapons testing as well as the construction of nuclear power plants. The group has fostered physician exchange programs between the United States and the Soviet Union in the interest of world peace. PSR continues to disseminate medical and scientific information about the dangers of nuclear war and seeks to educate an international constituency which includes medical professionals, government and military leaders, journalists and the general public.
As chapter chairman of PSR-Detroit, Felix Rogers was active in the development of the local organization. He participated in physician exchange programs with Soviet doctors on several occasions. He was a frequent speaker on television and radio regarding the medical consequences of a nuclear disaster. While chapter chairman, Rogers also organized a variety of symbolic demonstrations such as tree plantings and the release of balloons at the site of the Fermi II nuclear power plant. Rogers and other group members often registered complaints with government officials from France, the Soviet Union and the United States regarding the testing of nuclear arms.
In addition to his activities in PSR, Rogers also held various offices in both the local chapter and the national organization of the Episcopal Peace Fellowship. The purposes of the fellowship are to pray, study and work for peace; to aid Episcopalian conscientious objectors; to live out the Episcopal Church statements regarding peace and justice; and to aid other peace organizations in accomplishing specific goals. In practice, the fellowship organized adult education programs and developed various types of publicity designed to inform Episcopal congregations and the general public about peace issues. Christ Church Cranbrook in Bloomfield Hills, Michigan was the center for Rogers' local efforts on behalf of the fellowship.
Roger's involvement in peace action led his founding role in the Cranbrook Peace Foundation. In 1987, the Cranbrook Peace Foundation was incorporated as a non-profit, tax-exempt foundation; it described its purpose as "an endowment to kindle the promise of peace." Felix Rogers served as the Executive Director during the early years of the Foundation. The Foundation has two primary goals, that of education and that of supporting the peace-making activities of organizations in southeastern Michigan.
To support its educational goals, the Foundation sponsored an annual public lecture, presented by a prominent individual who made significant contributions to the cause of peace on either a national or global scale. The Peace Lecture was a significant event: it served as a fundraiser, through ticket sales for the lecture as well as dinner and a reception, but it was also a large expense, requiring additional preparatory fundraising. Speakers received honorariums and their travel expenses were paid. Pete Seeger, who spoke in 2000, declined an honorarium, but instead asked that Rogers bring audience members to the lecture who would not have otherwise attended, either for financial or political reasons. Other Annual Lecture speakers included Elie Wiesel, Jean Bertrand Aristide, Archbishop Desmond Tutu, Sister Helen Prejean, Jonathan Schell, and Dennis Kucinich. Speakers were selected by the Annual Lecture Subcommittee, one of several subcommittees that comprised the Cranbrook Peace Foundation.
To support the foundation's second goal, the CPF raised funds which it then distributed to local non-profit organizations through a grant review process, beginning in 1989. The grants that the Foundation awarded supported a range of diverse peace-related projects, such as conflict resolution programs, art exhibitions, conferences, teach-ins, and global dispute mediation and resolution efforts. Calls for proposals were announced twice yearly, and the Grant Review Committee met to rank proposals according to the goals and priorities of the CPF:
Halting militarism and the proliferation of arms.
Developing a broader local peace movement base.
Supporting nonviolent conflict resolution.
Encouraging a broader understanding and acceptance of nonviolence.
Promoting economic and social justice and human rights
________________________________________
(Take from "Grant Review Committee Evaluation Criteria and Format." Folder "Grant Evaluation Criteria" folder, Box 4).
The Felix J. Rogers papers document Rogers' activities in local peace movements from the 1980s until 2005. The collection has been divided into four series of material which document aspects of Rogers' personal life and the three peace organizations with which Rogers was most closely associated: Physicians for Social Responsibility-Detroit, the Episcopal Peace Fellowship, and the Cranbrook Peace Foundation.
Subjects:
Cranbrook Peace Foundation.; Detroit (Mich.); Episcopal Peace Fellowship.; Nuclear power plants.; Nuclear disarmament.; Physicians for Social Responsibility (U.S.); Physicians--Michigan--Detroit.; Peace--Societies, etc.; Rogers, Felix J., 1947-
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Cranbrook Peace Foundation.; Peace.; Physicians for Social Responsibility (U.S.)
Contributors - Sound Recordings
Ashrawi, Hanan.; Kushner, Harold S.; Mitchell, George J. (George John), 1933-; Prejean, Helen.; Prothrow-Stith, Deborah, 1954-; Schell, Jonathan, 1943-2014
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Posters.; Sound recordings.; Videotapes.
- Personal
  Personal files contain biographical material, correspondence relating to Rogers' medical practice, his travels to the former USSR, as well as other items from his family and personal life.
  - USSR 1987 (Box 1)
  - News clippings--biographical 1987 (Box 1)
  - Curriculum vitae undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, medical practice 1987-1990 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, medical practice 1988-1991 (Box 1)
  - Marygrove College Choir, Russian trip 1988 (Box 1)
  - Marygrove College, honorary degree 1990 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, Lithuania 1986-1989 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, general 1988-1997 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, Minsk 1989 (Box 1)
  - Personal and family items 1900, undated (Box 1)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 1)
    (Marygrove College Choir; Rogers at Japanese shrine)
- Cranbrook Peace Foundation
  Cranbrook Peace Foundation records have been divided into eight subseries.
  - Audiovisual
    Audiovisual contains several VHS and audio tapes of the Annual Lecture, from 1993-1999, as well as two audio tapes from other events.
    - Videotapes, VHS tapes
      - "Are Nuclear Weapons Immoral?" panel April 12, 1986 (Box 1)
        (at Metropolitan Methodist Church)
      - 1994 Annual Peace Lecture (Deborah Prothrow-Stith) (Box 1)
      - 1995 Annual Peace Lecture (Hanan Mikhail-Ashrawi) (Box 1)
      - 1996 Annual Peace Lecture (Sister Helen Prejean) (Box 1)
      - 1997 Annual Peace Lecture (Rabbi Harold Kushner) (Box 1)
      - 1998 Annual Peace Lecture (Jonathan Schell) (Box 1)
      - 1999 Annual Peace Lecture (Senator George Mitchell) (Box 1)
    - Audio tapes
      - Dr. Bochkov with Hal Youngblood September 25, 1985 (Box 1)
      - Archbishop Desmond Tutu, Cranbrook Peace Lecture July 15, 1993 (Box 1)
      - Ike Krasner and panel--Nuclear holocaust implications undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    Correspondence files cover the years 1987-2005 and contains letters, faxes, and emails concerning CPF business.
    - 1987-2005 undated, 10 folders (Box 2)
    - Letters from early period of CPF 1988-1989 (Box 2)
      (includes letter from Senator Carl Levin)
    - Memos to Board of Trustees 1987-2005 (Box 2)
    - Nobel Prize Nominations 2001 (Box 2)
  - Administration
    Administration contains files from the Board of Trustees, the governing body of the CPF, as well as agendas, memos, and minutes from the Annual Meeting of the CPF. Legal and tax documentation is included in this subseries as well.
    - Legal and Tax Documents 1988-2003 (scattered dates) (Box 2)
    - Leadership and Governance 1987-2003 (Box 2)
    - Youth Leadership Project (YLP) 2002-2004 (Box 2)
    - Meeting Agendas (Jackie Rubio, Felix Rogers, Robert Shank) 1995-1996 (Box 2)
    - Annual Meeting
      (includes memos, agendas, and minutes)
      - 1987-1990 (Box 2)
      - 1991-1994 (Box 2)
      - 1995-1998 (Box 2)
    - Board of Trustees
      - Agendas and minutes
        - 1990-1995 (Box 3)
        - 1996-1999 (Box 3)
        - 2000-2005 (Box 3)
      - Roster 1995-2003 (scattered dates) (Box 3)
    - Membership Reports 1987-1994 (Box 3)
    - Cranbrook Peace Foundation Focus Group 1995 (Box 3)
    - Executive Director's Newsletter 1995-1996 (Box 3)
    - Presentations undated (Box 3)
  - Grant Review Committee
    Grant Review Committee records contain proposals received by CPF, the rating system used to determine successful proposals, correspondence between the CPF and the grant applicants, as well as reports from the grantees to the CPF. This subseries also includes material on the Conflict Resolution Database, a project that was funded by the CPF and completed by outside consultants. In addition to the correspondence that pertains to the winning bid for the contract, there are also printed copies of the database contents.
    - Call for proposals
      - Grant applications and related correspondence (Box 3)
      - 1989 (Box 3)
      - 1990, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - 1991, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - 1992 (Box 3)
      - 1993, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - 1994, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - 1995, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - 1996 (Box 4)
      - 1997 (Box 4)
      - 1998 (Box 4)
      - 1999, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - 2000 (Box 4)
      - 2001, 4 folders (Box 4)
      - 2002, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - 2003 (Box 4)
      - 2004 (Box 4)
      - 2005 (Box 4)
    - Reports from grantees 1993-2001 (Box 4)
    - Grant evaluation criteria 1995-1998 (Box 4)
    - Blank grant applications and guidelines 1993-1998, undated (Box 4)
    - Conflict Resolution Database 1995, 1 folders (Box 4)
    - Conflict Resolution Database 1995, 2 volumes (Box 5)
  - Finance and Fundraising
    Finance and Fundraising files document the CPF's financial viability, as well as sources of funding for the foundation's endowment. The CPF fundraising letters, written by Felix Rogers can be found in this subseries. Correspondence related to the Chrysler Fund is also included.
    - Financial Reports
      (some include related correspondence, minutes of finance committee)
      - 1988-1991 (Box 5)
      - 1992-1994 (Box 5)
      - 1995-1996 (Box 5)
      - 1997 (Box 5)
      - 1998-1999 (Box 5)
      - 2000-2004 (Box 5)
    - Non-violent conflict resolution proposal 1995-1996 (Box 5)
    - Chrysler Fund 1997-2002 (Box 5)
    - Biographical sketches of board members 1998 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence regarding funding sources (Box 5)
    - Drafts of fundraising materials (Box 5)
    - Appeals for donations 1990-2004 (fundraising letters) (Box 5)
    - Letters of thanks to donors 1988-1997 (Box 5)
    - Grant Requests from CPF 1987-1995 (scattered dates) (Box 5)
  - Newsletter
    Material in the Newsletter subseries includes drafts and correspondence pertaining to recruiting and arranging content for the foundation's newsletter; researchers will also find scattered issues of the printed final version of the newsletter from 1988 until 2005 in these files.
    - CPF logo--slides (Box 5)
    - Collected materials for CPF logo (Box 5)
    - Crane facts (Box 5)
      (to appear in Newsletter)
    - Newsletter drafts and correspondence 1990-2004, 10 folders (Box 5)
    - Printed newsletter issues
      - 1989-1996 (Box 5)
      - 1997-2005 (Box 5)
  - Annual Peace Award and Lecture
    Annual Peace Lecture contains planning and publicity materials for the annual lecture given by the foundation, as well as photographs from a small number of the lectures. The planning and publicity materials include correspondence, notes, Annual Lecture Committee memos and agendas, as well as printed material for the lectures. All lectures from 1988 until 2005 are represented; however, the lectures from 1993-2000 are better documented.
    - Planning and publicity materials
      - 1988 John Kenneth Galbraith (Box 6)
      - 1989 Paul Warnke (Box 6)
      - 1990 Elie Wiesel (Box 6)
      - 1991 Oscar Arias Sanchez (Box 6)
      - 1992 Jean-Bertrand Aristide (Box 6)
      - 1993 Archbishop Desmond Tutu, 4 folders (Box 6)
        (includes autographed copy of "Crying in the Wilderness")
      - 1994 Deborah Prothrow-Stith (Box 6)
      - 1995 Hanan Mikhail-Ashrawi (Box 6)
      - 1996 Sister Helen Prejean (Box 6)
      - 1997 Harold Kushner (Box 6)
      - 1998 Jonathan Schell (Box 6)
      - 1999 Senator George Mitchell (Box 6)
      - 2000 Pete Seeger (Box 6)
      - 2001 William Schulz (Box 6)
      - 2002 Dennis Kucinich (Box 6)
      - 2003 David Hamburg (Box 6)
      - 2004 Kathy Kelly (Box 6)
    - Related correspondence 2005 (Box 6)
      (Doctors Without Borders, represented by Darin Portnoy)
    - Annual lecture reports 1988-2001 (Box 6)
    - Felix Rogers' introductory speeches, notes 1988-2003 (Box 6)
    - Annual Peace Lecture, assorted publicity 1990-1995 (Box 6)
    - Photographs
      - Peace Lecture 1989 (Box 6)
      - Elie Wiesel portraits, Wiesel and Oscar Arias Sanchez receptions 1990-1991 (Box 6)
      - Peace Lecture 1994 (Box 6)
      - Peace Lecture 1995 (Box 6)
      - Peace Lecture 1996 (Box 6)
      - Pete Seeger, William Schulz 2000-2001 (Box 6)
      - Peace Lecture undated (Box 6)
    - Programs 1989-2001 (Box 6)
    - Evaluation (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous
    Miscellaneous contains news clippings, material pertaining to the CPF website, documents about peace activities in which the foundation participated but are not directly related to the central operations of CPF, notes, brochures, and anonymous writings.
    - Notes 1995, undated (Box 6)
    - News clippings 1988-2001 (Box 6)
    - Website 2000 (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous peace activities 2001, undated (Box 6)
    - Writings (Box 6)
    - Brochures (Box 6)
    - Statements against the death penalty 1996 (Box 6)
    - Photographs-- Youth/Conflict Resolution activities, 2002, undated (Box 6)
      (includes photos of PVC Players)
    - Posters
      - Archbishop Desmond Tutu, Annual Peace Lecture 1993 (Folder 1)
        (autographed)
      - Dennis Kucinich, "Let Us Declare Our Intent for Peace," 2002 (Folder 1)
- Physicians for Social Responsibility-Detroit
  Physicians for Social Responsibility - Detroit is comprised of correspondence, Executive Committee Meeting materials, and other documentation of PSR peace action. The correspondence includes both internal correspondence and letters to governmental officials regarding the dangers of a nuclear disaster. "Executive Committee Meetings" includes minutes of meetings and financial reports of the chapter. "Fermi II Nuclear Power Plant" includes information about an April 26, 1986 demonstration at this site and an audio tape entitled "Power Plant Reggae" by Malvina Reynolds. Researchers interested in the month-by-month activities of the chapter should consult the organization's newsletters represented here by an incomplete run of issues from 1985 to 1996. "Photographs" includes a few prints of a tree planting ceremony and one other chapter gathering.
  - Rogers-Patterson article draft undated (Box 7)
    (Chernobyl and radiation sickness)
  - Notes and collected materials regarding Chernobyl 1991, undated (Box 7)
  - Correspondence with Russian doctors 1989-1991 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence 1983 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence 1987-1995, 7 folders (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, Riga 1988-1989 (Box 7)
  - Official PSR correspondence 1991-1996 (scattered dates) (Box 7)
  - Executive Committee Meetings 1982-1996 (scattered dates), 7 folders (Box 7)
    (includes financial reports)
  - "The Day Before" project 1983 (Box 7)
  - Congressional outreach re: nuclear arms reduction 1983 (Box 7)
  - Dr. Helen Caldicott Lecture, Detroit 1983 (Box 7)
    (includes planning materials, correspondence, and audiotape recording of lecture)
  - "Nuclear War: Your Doctor is Concerned" campaign 1982-1984 (Box 7)
  - Non-Detroit PSR and International Physicians for the Prevention of Nuclear War 1985 (Box 7)
  - Eugene Perrin dinner 1990 (Box 7)
  - Irkutsk exchange 1987-1991 (Box 7)
  - PSR visit to USSR undated (Box 7)
  - Fermi II Nuclear Power Plant 1988 (Box 7)
    (includes information about "Detroit Remembers Chernobyl" Demonstration of April 26, 1988 and the audio tape, "Power Plant Reggae" by Malvina Reynolds)
  - Nuclear non-proliferation treaty 1995 (Box 7)
  - Newsletters 1988-1996 (scattered) (Box 7)
  - Meeting and lecture publicity 1983-1991, undated (Box 7)
  - News clippings 1989-1993 (Box 7)
  - Collected materials 1986-1998 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous 1982-1990 (Box 7)
    (includes audiotape of Dr. Jerome Frank at Detroit PSR Conference)
  - Miscellaneous 1990-1994 (Box 7)
  - Photographs, 1988-1990, undated (Box 7)
  - Photographs, Ceasefire Now and IPPNW Conference, Hiroshima, Japan circa 1990 (Box 7)
- Episcopal Peace Fellowship 1982-1991
  Episcopal Peace Fellowship records have been divided into correspondence, miscellaneous, newsletters, and printed material. The miscellaneous folder includes the amended by-laws of the fellowship as well as membership lists and flyers. The newsletters date from 1986 to 1991, but are not complete.
  - Correspondence 1982-1991 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous 1981-1985 (Box 7)
    (includes amended by-laws of May 1983)
  - Newsletters 1982-1991 (scattered) (Box 7)
  - Printed Materials 1983-1987 (Box 7)